It’s Professor Dave, let’s check out Legionnaires’ Disease.
Legionnaires’ disease, also called Legionellosis,
is a severe, often lethal form of pneumonia,
which just means lung inflammation.
Symptoms may include cough, muscle aches,
diarrhea, fever, and chills.
In the U.S., somewhere between 10,000 and
18,000 people get infected each year, some
of which end up in intensive care units.
We first learned about this disease in 1976,
when a mysterious outbreak of pneumonia occurred
at an American Legion convention in Philadelphia,
hence the name.
Because of the fatal nature of some of the
cases, health officials launched an intensive
investigation that resulted in the definition
of a new family of pathogenic bacteria, the
Legionellaceae.
The family Legionellaceae consists of a single
genus, Legionella, with 48 species and 70
serogroups.
These bacteria are slender gram-negative rods
that are pleomorphic, which means they can
change shape in response to their environment.
Infection with Legionella pneumophila has
three possible outcomes: One is no symptoms at all.
Two, an influenza-like illness called Pontiac
fever.
And three, legionnaires’ disease, a severe
form of pneumonia.
Legionella is naturally found in freshwater
lakes and streams, but can be particularly
dangerous to humans when it spreads in man-made
building water systems like cooling towers,
plumbing systems, hot water heaters, or decorative
fountains.
In particular, these bacteria thrive in the
mist created by air-conditioning ducts, and
can infect an entire building of people, like
that fateful summer of 1976 in Philadelphia.
A person becomes infected by breathing in
small droplets of water that contain Legionella,
and typically can’t spread the disease to
other people.
Legionnaires’ disease most often develops
in people with an already increased likelihood
of developing respiratory sickness, such as
those who smoke cigarettes or those with a
compromised immune system.
The Legionella, if able to establish an infection,
replicate within cells of the immune system.
After an incubation period of two to ten days,
an infection of L. pneumophila can cause acute
illness, which can escalate to multi-organ
disease of the gastrointestinal tract, liver,
central nervous system, or the kidneys.
To diagnose a case of Legionnaires’ disease,
clinicians typically take a chest x-ray, and
might conduct a urine test or saliva test
to confirm the presence of the bacteria.
Typically, antibiotics can clear an infection
of legionnaires’ disease, but approximately
10% of people who get sick with the disease
will die due to complications.
The best way to prevent Legionnaires’ disease
is to properly maintain building water systems,
hot tubs, and fountains.
So if you have many hot tubs and fountains
in your mansion, be sure to take precautions now.